<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before the queenes maiestie at Hampton Court, on Sunday the 16. day of October: By I. Hopkins, one of his maiesties chaplaines in ordinarie</title>
            <author>Hopkins, John, fl. 1604-1609.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1609</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 42 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03640</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13768</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114087</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849315</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849315</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14455</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03640)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14455)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1276:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before the queenes maiestie at Hampton Court, on Sunday the 16. day of October: By I. Hopkins, one of his maiesties chaplaines in ordinarie</title>
                  <author>Hopkins, John, fl. 1604-1609.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[48] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by F. K[ingston] for Thomas Man,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1609.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C (A1 and C8 blank).</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; title page torn and stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14455:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14455:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED BEFORE THE QVEENES MAIESTIE at Hampton Court, on Sunday <hi>the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> day of October:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By I. HOPKINS, one of his Maieſties Chaplaines in ordinarie.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 3.18.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Many walke of whom I haue tolde you of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> now tell you weeping, that they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the enemies of the croſſe of Christ.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>AT LONDON <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> printed by <hi>F. K.</hi> for <hi>Thomas Man.</hi> 1609.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:14455:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14455:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE MIGH<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIE, HIGH-BORNE, VERTVOVS, AND MOST excellent Princeſſe: ANNE, by</hi> the grace of God, Queene of great <hi>Brittaine, France and Ireland.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Our Maiesties atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue hearing, and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious approouing this plaine Sermon, when it was preached before your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſse, mine own experience of your religious deuotion in frequenting the ſeruice of God: and your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb facs="tcp:14455:3"/>godly affection to goodbooks, and dailie reading them, which hath been often teſtified by ſuch as are acquainted with your Maiesties ſtudies: haue emboldned mee to print this Sermon, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent it to your Maiestie, earnest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie deſiring that it may bee as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable for the increaſe of godlines in ſuch as reade it, as it will be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to manie, being graced with your Maiesties name and patronage.</p>
            <p>The Lord of heauen and earth ſo bleſſe your Maiesty with a dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie increaſe of his graces, that as your Highneſse hath the happines to be the moſt worthie and famous Queene of Europe, ſo after manie
<pb facs="tcp:14455:3"/>yeeres enioying your Crowne vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on earth, you may bee crowned with eternal glory in heauen. For which none ſhall more heartily pray, then</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Maieſties most humble ſeruant, <hi>I. HOPKINS.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:14455:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14455:4"/>
            <head>A SERMON PREA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHED BEFORE THE Queenes Maieſtie at Hampton <hi>Court, on Sunday the</hi> 16. day of October.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>GEN. 5.24.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And Henoch walked with God, and he was no more ſeene: for God tooke him away.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is an obſeruation no leſſe auncient, then true, that ſuch as ſearch into the bowels of the earth for mettals, after long labours, and great paines doe finde <hi>paruum in magno,</hi> a little mettall in much oare: but, ſaith S. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> in his fifteenth <hi>Homilie</hi> vpon <hi>Geneſis:</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:14455:5"/>they that labour in the ſacred mine of the holy Scriptures ſhall finde <hi>magnum in paruo,</hi> a great treaſure of doctrine in a few words, many di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine inſtructions in a ſhort ſentence. And this (moſt Gratious and Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable) is this day fulfilled in our eares; this parcell of Scripture very ſhort, and yet the matter ſo large, as will bee hardly deliuered within the vſuall time limited for a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon. The words are an hiſtoricall record of an holy man, that liued in the firſt age of the world, whoſe life for an example is left to perpetuall memorie. For as the doctrines in the Scriptures are for the information of our iudgements, ſo are the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples for the reformation of our affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions. And no doubt good exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples where they are well obſerued, and carefully applied, are ſtrong mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues to vertue and godlines. And it is vndoubtedly one of the cauſes of the common corruption of this age,
<pb facs="tcp:14455:5"/>that there are ſo many examples of prophane impietie, and ſo few pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidents of religious vertue. But that we may the better vnderſtand, and remember that which wee ſhall heare from this Scripture, we wil ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue therein two parts: The life of <hi>Henoch</hi> for our example; (<hi>Henoch walked with God.</hi>) And his end for our comfort; <hi>He was no more ſeene: for God tooke him away.</hi> His life conſidered, firſt in it ſelfe, that <hi>he walked with God:</hi> Next with certaine circumſtances, neceſſarilie obſerued for his greater commendations, as ſhall afterward appeare. In the ſecond part, The thing it ſelfe, <hi>that he was no more ſeene.</hi> And the reaſon of the ſame, <hi>for God tooke him away. And Henoch walked with God,</hi> &amp;c. This phraſe is vſuall in the Hebrew tongue. To walke, ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth to hold a courſe of life. <hi>To walke in the counſell of the wicked,</hi> is to liue in the counſell of the wicked. <hi>To walke in the waies of the Kings of Iſrael,</hi> is to
<pb facs="tcp:14455:6"/>liue like the Kings of Iſrael. <hi>To walke after Baalim,</hi> is to practiſe the Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie of <hi>Baalim. To walke with God,</hi> is to liue according to Gods will, both in worſhipping of him as he hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, and practiſing ſuch morall duties as he hath preſcribed; And to walke at all times and in all places, as in the preſence of God, who is an eye witnes of our moſt ſecret acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;
<note place="margin">Pſalm. 139.</note> for though all men walke in Gods ſight (as who can hide him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe from him <hi>whoſe eyes behold all places,
<note place="margin">Prou.</note> ſpying out the euill and the good?</hi>) yet the moſt ſort of men,
<note place="margin">Iob 39.</note> like the <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strich,</hi> mentioned by <hi>Elihu</hi> in the booke of <hi>Iob, either know it not, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard it not.</hi> But that the meaning of theſe words may more clearely ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare vnto vs, let vs looke into other places of holy Scripture, where the like wordes are ſet downe and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, ſo ſhal we ſee how the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Ghoſt (the beſt Interpreter of the Scriptures) will teach vs to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand
<pb facs="tcp:14455:6"/>them. In the third chapter of the firſt booke of the Kings, <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith thus vnto the Lord:
<note place="margin">King. 3.6.</note> 
               <hi>Thou hast ſhewed to thy ſeruant Dauid my father great mercie when he walked before thee in truth, and in righteouſnes, and in vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſſe of heart with thee.</hi> And in chapter 9. the Lord ſaith to him,
<note place="margin">1. King. 9.4.</note> 
               <hi>If thou wilt walke before mee, as Dauid thy father walked in pureneſſe of heart, and in righteouſneſſe, to doe according to all that I haue commanded thee, &amp;c.</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in the ſecond of the Kings, and the twentieth chapter <hi>Hezechiah</hi> ſaith, <hi>I beſeech thee O Lord remember now how I haue walked before thee in truth, and with a perfect heart, and haue done that which is good in thy ſight.</hi> So that by all theſe places it is euident, that to walke with God implies three duties, <hi>truth</hi> for the foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>righteouſneſse</hi> and holineſſe of life for the outward conuerſation, and <hi>ſinceritie</hi> in the heart without diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation. <hi>Henoch</hi> then is commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb facs="tcp:14455:7"/>for theſe three things, <hi>ſoundneſſe</hi> of religion, <hi>ſinceritie</hi> of heart, and <hi>godlineſſe</hi> of life. And this was the walking that was commanded to <hi>Abraham,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 17.1. Gen. 6.9.</note> commended in <hi>Noah,</hi> and worthilie recorded by this example of <hi>Henoch</hi> for our inſtruction: firſt, that wee ſettle our faith vpon true grounds:
<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 10.1.</note> ſecondly, that we take heed of hypocriſie, which <hi>like a dead flie corrupteth all the boxe of ointment:</hi> laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that our conuerſation be in holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, <hi>without which no man ſhall ſee God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 12.14.</note> If wee build on a falſe foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation,
<note place="margin">Matth. 7.</note> 
               <hi>the building will fall.</hi> If our profeſſion be in hypocriſie, <hi>our hope will be as the web of a ſpider.</hi> And if we ioyne not vertue to our faith,
<note place="margin">Iob 18.14. 2. Pet. 1. Iames.</note> it will be <hi>a dead, or a diuels faith.</hi> Therefore wee may hence conclude, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther heretikes, hypocrites, nor pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane perſons <hi>walke with God,</hi> and they that <hi>walke not with God</hi> in the kingdome of grace, ſhall neuer reſt with him in the kingdome of glorie.
<pb facs="tcp:14455:7"/>In the application therefore of this point, ſuch as by reaſon of careleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to heare, and learne good things, are yet ignorant of the grounds of religion, and therefore may eaſilie be led into error, are to be admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed to lay a better, and more ſure foundation againſt the time of triall. For aſſuredly ſo many could not be ſeduced (as daily are in theſe times) if euer they had learned and belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the true grounds and foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the faith.
<note place="margin">Act. 17.11.</note> Alſo we ought like y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> men of Berea to make triall of the truth of thoſe things wee hold and haue learned by the rules of faith, &amp; willinglie ſuffer our ſelues to bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in the eſſentiall grounds of true religion. For although that er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors in ſome circumſtances are not ſo dangerous (ſo as they bee not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful) for who in ſome things may not bee deceiued?) yet to erre in the foundation is the certaine ruine of the whole worke, and ſo to die is the
<pb facs="tcp:14455:8"/>vndoubted deſtruction both of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die and ſoule. Secondly, wee muſt bee ſure that in this walking with God our heart be ſound.
<note place="margin">Prou. 4.23.</note> 
               <hi>Of all watch and ward</hi> (ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi>) <hi>looke to thy heart.</hi> For if that bee ſincere, it is ſo highlie acceptable with God, that in mercie hee paſſeth by many imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections. And it was a ſpeciall part of the laſt admonition that <hi>Dauid</hi> gaue vnto <hi>Salomon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Chron. 28.9.</note> to <hi>ſerue the Lord with a perfect heart.</hi> Diſſembled ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines is double impietie, and though ſuch paintings may deceiue men, they can neuer deceiue the al ſeeing eies of the eternall God. Laſtlie, that this our walking may be pleaſing to the Lord on al parts, we muſt <hi>do</hi> that which is good in Gods ſight, that is, we muſt not only auoid ſuch things, as the eies of the Lord cannot abide to behold, but we muſt likewiſe pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe &amp; performe thoſe good workes that he hath commanded vs, and are belonging to our ſeuerall callings.
<pb facs="tcp:14455:8"/>
               <hi>Wee are created to good workes to liue in them;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.10. Pſal. 34.14. &amp; Iſa. 1.16.</note> not onely muſt wee <hi>ceaſe from euill, but doe good:</hi> remembring the puniſhment of that ſeruant who <hi>hid his maſters talent in a napkin.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 19.20.</note> For ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our ſeuerall places, gifts, and meanes, the Lord requires of vs to ſeeke his glorie; and as wee deſire that the Lord will beſtow vpon vs glorie in heauen, ſo muſt we alwaies endeuour to aduance his glorie here vpon earth. But it will be ſaid, <hi>Durus eſt hic ſermo:</hi> this is a hard ſaying, who can thus walke? And if none ſhall enioy the kingdome of heauen but ſuch as walke thus vpon earth, then who ſhal be ſaued? It is true indeed, there are none that make ſuch ſtraight ſteps to their feete, but ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times they ſlide, or ſtep out of the way, neither is any man ſo vpright vpon earth that doth good and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth not: <hi>In ſome things we offend all,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iam. 3.2.</note> ſaith the Apoſtle. But it followeth not, becauſe wee cannot line in the
<pb facs="tcp:14455:9"/>perfect obedience of the law of God, therefore wee ſhould not labour to doe our vttermoſt endeuour, and (as I take it) the word vſed in the origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall text will giue ſome light hereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> which properly ſignifieth, <hi>made himſelfe to walke,</hi> implying not a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of the worke, but a diligence in the endeuour to reſiſt the tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of ſinne, and fight againſt the luſts of the fleſh. And this is the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling of that which the Scripture teacheth, that the life of a Chriſtian is a continuall warfare, the profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whereof wee vndertake in our Baptiſme,
<note place="margin">1. Tim. 1.18. 2. Tim. 4.7. 1. Cor. 9.24. Luk. 13.24.</note> and the execution where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of muſt be the daylie practiſe of our liues. The life of a Chriſtian is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to running in a race, ſet out by the words of labouring, <hi>ſtriuing, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuouring,</hi> &amp; here by <hi>walking:</hi> for the paſſage to heauen is painefull on foote in the worke of mortification, not riding at eaſe in following the pleaſures and luſts of the fleſh. <hi>In my
<pb facs="tcp:14455:9"/>bed by night I ſought him that my ſoule loued,
<note place="margin">Cant. 3.1.</note> I ſought him but I found him not,</hi> ſaith the ſpouſe of Chriſt, teaching that ſuch as will find Chriſt, muſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe from their bed, (by which is meant, pleaſures and delights of the fleſh) and ſeeke him in the exerciſes of faſting and prayer, and ſuch like duties of holines. The way to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen would neuer haue been called a narrow way, nor the gate a ſtraite gate if it were ſufficient, in words to profeſſe true religion, and in our workes to denie our hearts no plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. Hitherto we haue heard the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious and godly life of this holy man, and how hee walked with God. But as all vertues and vices are aggrauated, or extenuated by their circumſtances; ſo in the obſeruation of the matter precedent in this hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorie ſome neceſſarie points may be noted, by which the excellencie of this his walking may much more bee admired, &amp; they are ſpecially three.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:14455:10"/>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>The condition and ſtate of life wherein he lined.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>The men with whom he liued.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>The time how long he continued.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Firſt, for his eſtate, it is apparent that hee was a great Prince of his time; the eldeſt of his houſe; of the firſt line in the deſcent from <hi>Adam:</hi> that hee enioyed abundantly the plentie of the earth, that then was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding fertile in yeelding all kinde of fruites, as being not yet ſowred with the vnſauorie corrupt matter the vniuerſall deluge left vpon it (for howſoeuer we reade of ſinne in that age of the world, we reade of no fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine) and being the heire of his houſe, and firſt borne of the familie, his authoritie and power was great. Now that wealth, greatnes, and plentie, are ſtrong temptations to our nature to take libertie to ſinne, may appeare by that warning which <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> gaue the people: <hi>And when the Lord thy God hath brought thee into the
<pb facs="tcp:14455:10"/>land which hee ſware vnto thy fathers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deur. 6.10.11.12.</note> &amp;c. <hi>with great, and goodly cities which thou buildedſt not: and houſes full of all manner of goods which thou filledst not,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And when thou hast eaten, and art full, Then beware leſt thou forget the Lord.</hi> And the danger of this temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation made <hi>Agur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 30.</note> as it is in the <hi>Prouerbs,</hi> to miſlike aſwel abundance of riches, as extremitie of want, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a great occaſion of pride, and forgetfulneſſe of God: For what made <hi>Nabal</hi> ſo <hi>proude that a man might not ſpeak to him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 25.17.</note> but his wealth? what made <hi>Haman</hi> the ſonne of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medatha</hi> ſo proud, but his greatnes, by reaſo of the Kings fauor? Wealth and libertie are the parents of many ſinnes, and are indeed thoſe thornes that choake the good ſeede of the word,
<note place="margin">Luke 8.14.</note> not in their owne nature, (for ſo they are the good bleſſings of God) but by the corruption of our nature that is ſo apt to abuſe them. <hi>There is an euill ſicknes that I haue ſeene
<pb facs="tcp:14455:11"/>vnder the Sunne,
<note place="margin">Eccle. 5.12.</note> riches reſerued to the owners thereof for their euill,</hi> ſaith <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon.</hi> This indeede hath not been true in all, <hi>Abraham, Iob, Dauid, Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoſaphat, Ioſeph</hi> of <hi>Arimathea</hi> and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie other haue bin rich, and yet wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked with God as <hi>Enoch</hi> did: and rich <hi>Abraham</hi> receiued poore <hi>Lazarus</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his boſom, to ſhew that neither of both the eſtates, either of riches, or pouerty ſtop vp the way to the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen. But if riches were not a dangerous impediment our Sauior would not haue ſaid, <hi>It is har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der for a Camel to paſſe thorow the eie of a needle, then for a rich man to enter into the Kingdome of God.</hi> Now for the curing of this ſickneſſe (as <hi>Salomon</hi> calles it) theſe remedies are to bee v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. Firſt, to remember we are ſtew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards of theſe bleſſings, and muſt giue account to God for the abuſing of them.</p>
            <p>Secondlie, wee muſt know that this is not our heauen: it is but as
<pb facs="tcp:14455:11"/>the paſſage thorow the wilderneſſe to the land of promiſe. For if we will needs haue a heauen here, wee may feare it will one day be ſaid to vs, as <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaid to the rich man,
<note place="margin">Luke 16.</note> 
               <hi>Sonne remember thou in thy life time receiuedſt thy pleaſures, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, we muſt vnderſtand that pleaſures are but like <hi>Eues</hi> Apple, pleaſant in ſhew &amp; taſte, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſe of extreame miſery: like <hi>Eſaus</hi> red broth, pleaſing his appetite, but the loſſe of his birthright: like the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites Quailes, that made them fat bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, but leane ſoules: like <hi>Ionathans</hi> honie, that cleared his eics, but had like to haue coſt him his life: like <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zechiels</hi> booke, ſweete in the mouth, but bitter in the belly: to conclude, like <hi>Ionas</hi> gourd, ſhort, ſlight &amp; mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentarie, dying in the birth, and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing in the cradle.</p>
            <p>Fourthlie, whereas there is a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vſe of pleaſure (which no ſound Diuine euer denied) yet wee muſt
<pb facs="tcp:14455:12"/>hearken to <hi>Salomon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rou.</note> who ſaith, <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stime is not meete for a foole:</hi> meaning ſuch as haue not godly wiſdome to vſe them: for euen as children will ſurfet themſelues with fruits, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperat perſons with drinke, ſo wil fooles doe with pleaſures. Now pleaſures and recreations are indeed ordained as ſweete ingredients to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate the bitterneſſe of humane mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talitie: and like as the immoderate vſe of ſweet meats cannot be health<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to the bodie, ſo is the daily fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing of pleaſures as hurtfull to the ſoule.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, (for I may not be ouer te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious) the meditation of our laſt end is a ſingular helpe to keepe vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bewitched with theſe <hi>Circes</hi> cups of pleaſures: <hi>Qui conſiderat qualis erit in morte, ſemper pauidus erit in operatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Greg. lib.</hi> 12. <hi>Mor.</hi>
               </note> ſaith S. <hi>Gregorie;</hi> He that conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth what hee ſhall bee in his death, will neuer bee without feare in the workes of his life: and moſt bitter
<pb facs="tcp:14455:12"/>will the remembrance of vaine plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures be, when death ſhal ceaſe vpon vs. The ſecond circumſtance wee conſidered, is the time when <hi>Henoch</hi> liued, <hi>viz.</hi> in a declining age of the world,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cal. in Gen. Exemplum ſingulare nobis in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſona vnius hominis ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuitur, qui in horrenda diſſipatione firmus ſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tit.</hi>
               </note> the children of <hi>Cain</hi> being many, his time paralleling with <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mech,</hi> that had corrupted the inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of mariage with polygamy, &amp; was (as by his owne boaſting may appeare) an inſolent tyrant. Now what an hindrance it is to godlineſſe to liue among wicked men,
<note place="margin">Gen. 4. Pſalm. 120.</note> 
               <hi>Dauids</hi> complaint, Pſalm. 120. and our dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce will ſufficientlie proue.
<note place="margin">Gen. 19.23.</note> 
               <hi>Lots</hi> daughters could neuer haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſed ſuch a way for their inceſt, if they had not ſeene the effects of drunkenneſſe in Sodom. The Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites by ſeeing the idolatrie of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptians did learne to make the gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den calfe in the wildernes;
<note place="margin">Exod. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 42.</note> and <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoahs</hi> court taught <hi>Ioſeph</hi> to call his brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſpies againſt his knowledge, and ſo often to proteſt the ſame by
<pb facs="tcp:14455:13"/>the life of <hi>Pharaoh.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Neh.</note> The children of Iſrael by liuing among the Heathen were readier in the ſpeech of <hi>Aſdod</hi> then in the language of Canaan; and <hi>Peter</hi> neuer denied his Maſter,
<note place="margin">Matth. 26.</note> till he kept companie with the high Prieſts ſeruants. Surely no contagion is more dangerous to the bodie, then the wicked examples of the vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie are to the ſoule; and who would make him his companion that is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſed with an infectious maladie A?s therefore we muſt take heede we be not ſtained with the euill examples of the vngodly, leſt being like vnto them in their liues, wee be <hi>made par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of their plagues,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apoc. 18.4.</note> ſo muſt wee bee carefull to auoid their company and fellowſhip,
<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 13.</note> leſt <hi>touching pitch wee bee defiled therewith. Dauid</hi> the King in ſetting downe the orders of his houſe,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 101.7.</note> ſaith, <hi>There ſhall no deceitfull perſon dwell in my houſe, hee that telleth lies, ſhall not tarrie in my ſight:</hi> and S. <hi>Paul</hi> admoniſhing vs not to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued,
<pb facs="tcp:14455:13"/>nor corrupted with the words of the wicked, addeth this ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueat as a meanes,
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.7<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Be not therefore com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions with them. Ieremies</hi> example is worthie to be remembred herein, who <hi>ſat not in the aſſembly of the mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 15.17.</note> But ſeeing ſo long as we liue in this world, there will bee euer ſome darnell among the corne, ſo that we cannot bee alwaies free from euill companie; Let vs remember the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie man <hi>Lot,</hi> who though he liued in Sodom, became not like the Sodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits, <hi>but his righteous ſoule was vext with ſeeing their vnlawfull deeds:
<note place="margin">2. Pet. 2.7.8.</note> Eliah</hi> the Prophet, <hi>Daniel</hi> with his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, and <hi>Henoch</hi> in this place, that continued their ſoundneſſe of religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and life without blemiſh, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all the euill examples of their time. And thus much for the ſecond circumſtance in this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample. The third and laſt is his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuerance, viz. that he liued this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie life, and continued this godlie
<pb facs="tcp:14455:14"/>courſe all his time which was more then three hundred yeeres. A good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſeuerance vndoubtedly, and an argument of a ſure building, that in ſo many yeeres was not ſhaken: many for a time haue runne well, and yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re they came to their races end, haue fallen foulie, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly to perſeuere, <hi>hic labor, hoc opus est.</hi> The people at the firſt hearing of the law were very zealous, and promiſed much; but, ſaith the Lord, <hi>O that there were in them ſuch an hart to feare mee and keepe all my commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments Alway! that it might goe well with them and their children for euer.</hi> Wherin the perſeuera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is noted to be the principal thing that the Lord looketh for at our hands. For to bee ſometimes mooued to deuotion and contrition, may ariſe from ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den affliction of ſickneſſe, impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or ſuch like, peraduenture by hearing of a Sermon, where the iudgements of God are zealouſlie
<pb facs="tcp:14455:14"/>denounced (as was <hi>Felix</hi> at the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon of S.
<note place="margin">Act. 24.</note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi>) ſo haue I ſeene at ſea many paſſionately affected with ſhew of repentance by occaſion of a violent ſtorme, and yet hath all been like a morning cloud,
<note place="margin">Hoſe. 6.4.</note> and as the morning dew hath vaniſhed away. And wee ſee how much corne is ſowne (as our Sauiour Chriſt teacheth) which though it take ſome ſhallow roote,
<note place="margin">Matth. 13.</note> neuer abideth to bring forth fruite. But to haue religion ſo ſetled in the heart, that the life be alwayes ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with an habituall practiſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, is that which God onely accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, and is here in this example ſet before vs. <hi>In caſſum bonum agitur</hi> (ſaith S.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Greg.</hi> 1. <hi>lib. Mor.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Gregorie</hi>) <hi>ſi ante vitae termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num deſeratur:</hi> It is in vaine to begin a courſe of godlines, and after with <hi>Demas</hi> to imbrace this preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t world. He runs in vaine that falles or failes ere he comes at his races end: and as thoſe whom God loueth, <hi>he loueth to
<pb facs="tcp:14455:15"/>the end,</hi> ſo thoſe that proſeſſe to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him muſt doe it to the end. <hi>Lots</hi> wife by looking backe was made an example to all backſliders, that the ſalt of her deſtruction might ſeaſon vs to a more conſtant reſolution. <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mineritis vxoris Lot,</hi> (ſaith a father) <hi>de Sodoma quidem eductae, quia Deo cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didit; ſed in via mutatae, quia retro aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pexit:</hi> Remember <hi>Lots</hi> wife, led out of Sodome, becauſe ſhe beleeued the Angels; but turned to a pillar of ſalt, becauſe ſhee looked backe. Good workes haue a reward if we faint not; but to begin in the ſpirit and end in the fleſh, is fearefull; and for ſuch it had been better <hi>they had neuer knowne the way of righteouſneſſe.</hi> Let vs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore rather endeuour to bee like the Church of <hi>Thyatira,</hi> whoſe laſt workes were more then the firſt: and remember, <hi>ſine perſeuerantia nec qui pugnat victoriam, nec palmam victor conſequitur:</hi> without perſeuerance, neither hee that fighteth getteth the
<pb facs="tcp:14455:15"/>victorie, nor the conqueror the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of triumph. For hee onely ſhall be crowned that continueth to the end. <hi>Ioas</hi> is not reckoned among the good kings, becauſe his zeale laſted no longer then <hi>Iehoida</hi> liued. Nor <hi>Nero</hi> among the good Emperours for his firſt fiue yeeres clemencie. <hi>The end of a thing</hi> (ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi>) is <hi>better then the beginning.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Quinque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uium Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronis. Suet.</hi> Eccleſiaſt. 7.10.1. Theſ. 5.</note> Therefore I will conclude this point with the warning of the Apoſtle, ſeeing that God by his ſpirit hath begun the worke of grace in vs, <hi>that wee quench not the ſpirit.</hi> And becauſe a fire is put out as well by withdrawing the fuel, as by powring on water,
<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.13.</note> wee muſt giue good heede to two other ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitions in that place: <hi>Pray continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, deſpiſe not propheſie:</hi> and that in the 1. to <hi>Timothie</hi> the 4. <hi>Giue atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance to reading, to exhortation, to do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</hi> For where prayer is deuoutly vſed, and the word carefully read, and heard, the increaſe of godlines
<pb facs="tcp:14455:16"/>will vndoubtedly follow; but when prayer is neglected, and preaching deſpiſed, all godly and religious mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions will ſoone be quenched. And thus much concerning the life of <hi>Henoch,</hi> wherein wee haue ſeene a rare and worthie preſident of true godlines. Now it remaineth to learne what fruit and effect followed the ſame. It hath been a common o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion among the Atheiſts that there is no God, becauſe neither is there puniſhment for vice, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward for vertue (as they affirme.)
<note place="margin">Mal. 3.14.</note> And the Prophet <hi>Malachi</hi> had to doe with ſuch in his time, that ſaid, <hi>it is in vaine to ſerue God.</hi> And ſuch were alſo in the Prophet <hi>Zephanies</hi> time,
<note place="margin">Zeph. 1.12.</note> that ſaid, <hi>The Lord will do neither good nor euill.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 9<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2.</note> And in the booke of Eccleſiaſtes the wiſe man iuſtly tax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth thoſe <hi>Epicures</hi> that ſaid, al things are alike <hi>to all, to the iuſt, and to the wicked, to the good, and to the pure, and to the polluted, and to him that ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth,
<pb facs="tcp:14455:16"/>and to him that ſacrificeth not, as is the good, ſo is the ſinner, he that ſweareth as he that feareth an oath.</hi> And it is to bee feared this opinion too com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monlie preuaileth in the world, and that is the cauſe why religion and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious actions be in ſo ſmall account as they are. But whoſoeuer ſhall take counſell from the holy Scriptures, ſhall find that this is nothing elſe but a meere ſophiſtication of Satan to bring godlineſſe into contempt. Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous are thoſe bleſſings that are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed in the law, to the religious keepers of the ſame,
<note place="margin">Leuit. 26. Deut. 28.</note> and euer true is that which was ſpoken to <hi>Heli</hi> from the Lord, <hi>Them that honour mee,
<note place="margin">1. Sam. 2.30. Ioh. 12.26.</note> I will honour, &amp;c.</hi> Which is alſo confirmed by that ſaying of our Sauiour, <hi>If any man ſerue me, him will my father honor.</hi> The examples in the Scriptures are many, that confirme vnto vs this truth. In the ſecond of Chron. the proſperitie of <hi>Iehoſaphat</hi> is wholly at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed to this, as the true cauſe of
<pb facs="tcp:14455:17"/>the ſame, <hi>becauſe he walked in the first waies of his father Dauid, and ſought not Baalim.</hi> And though his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome was but ſmall, not ſo much as the fourth part of this Iland, hee was able to bring into the field a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue eleue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hundred thouſand figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting men, God bleſſed ſo exceeding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie him and all his people, as in the ſame Chapter doth at large appeare. <hi>Noah, Abraham, Ioſeph, Ioſua,</hi> and <hi>Caleb</hi> are all confirmations hereof.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.56</note> 
               <hi>This I had becauſe I kept thy precepts,</hi> ſaith the Prophet <hi>Dauid,</hi> deriuing the ground and cauſe of his happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe from his true ſeruice of almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie God.
<note place="margin">Ier. 39.16.</note> 
               <hi>Ebedmelech</hi> the black-more was promiſed of God to bee deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red (at that great ſlaughter, &amp; ſacking of Ieruſalem) from thoſe that ſought his life, and that he ſhould not fal by the ſword, <hi>becauſe thou haſt put thy truſt in me,</hi> ſaith the Lord. And to conclude with the ſaying of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle,
<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.8.</note> 
               <hi>Godlineſſe hath the promiſe of
<pb facs="tcp:14455:17"/>this life, and of that which is to come.</hi> Thus by theſe (whereto might bee added many more teſtimonies and examples) it is plainelie proued that it is not in vaine to ſerue God. Now let vs ſee what y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was wherewith the religious life of <hi>Henoch</hi> was rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. <hi>And he was no more ſeen, &amp;c.</hi> This is the prerogatiue that <hi>Moſes</hi> ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to haue been beſtowed vpon <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noch</hi> by the Lord, as a rare fruit of his great ſinceritie and godlineſſe. <hi>viz,</hi> that hee was taken from among the ſocietie of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the middeſt of his age, which at the firſt ſight may ſeeme ſtrange; all men naturally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring long life, &amp; the wicked threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with this iudgement, that they ſhall not liue out halfe their daies. But if wee looke more throughly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this point,
<note place="margin">Pſalm.</note> we ſhal ſee that neither is long life alwaies a bleſſing, nor for the children of God to die in their youth, an argument of Gods diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure. For aſſuredlie this tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:14455:18"/>of <hi>Henoch</hi> was a ſingular fauour of God towards him, otherwiſe it ſhould neuer haue here by <hi>Moſes</hi> bin ſo particularly recorded,
<note place="margin">Heb. 11.</note> nor by S. <hi>Paul</hi> afterward ſo expreſſely recoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted among thoſe glorious achieue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of faith. For can any earthlie benefit be counterpoyſed with this fauour of God, To be receiued into heauenly glorie; from the worlds miſerie, into the ſocietie of Angels; from the companie of euill men, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to reſt, and peace; from this pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of trouble, into eternal ſafetie; from daily tentation, into the perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of contentation; from continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al diſcontentment, into the hauen of aſſured ſafetie, from the ſtormes of perpetual danger? vndoubtedly had I the tongues of men and Angels I could not to perfection ſet out the greatneſſe of this diſparitie. And that in the midſt of his age, for long life is but as a long warfare, as a long win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as a long impriſonment, as a long
<pb facs="tcp:14455:18"/>and tedious iournie at ſea, wherein all the hope of contentment ſtands on the ſafe arriuall in the harbour, and returning home into our coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie. Long life (I ſay) is not alwaies a bleſſing; for how many liue long to their greater miſerie in this life, and further puniſhment afterward? How much happier had it bin with <hi>Heli</hi> that hee had died young, then to haue liued to ſee the impietie of his ſonnes, and their miſerable end? How much happier with <hi>Saul</hi> if hee had died in the prime of his yeeres, then in liuing long, to commit ſo many fearefull ſinnes, and at length to be his owne murtherer? Ah how happie had it been with <hi>Zedekia</hi> if he had died in his cradle, rather then to liue to ſee Ieruſalem (through his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion and periurie) ſackt, that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Temple burnt, his owne chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren ſlaine before his face, and then (his eies being put out) to liue yet longer in miſerable captiuitie? How
<pb facs="tcp:14455:19"/>much better had it been with <hi>Ioas</hi> to haue died in <hi>Iehoiadas</hi> time; then in liuing after him,
<note place="margin">2. Chro. 24.</note> of a religious King to become a prophane Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>later and bloody man; and in the height of his ſinne, to bee ſlaine by the hands of murtherers? On the otherſide, the Scripture ſaith of the death of <hi>Ieroboams</hi> ſonne that died young,
<note place="margin">1. King. 14.13.</note> that <hi>hee only of Iero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boams houſe ſhould come to his graue, becauſe in him there was found ſome goodneſſe toward the Lord God of Iſrael.</hi> So as this was the fauour that God beſtowed on him to take him away a child, before hee was corrupted with his fathers idolatrie, or ſaw the diſaſtrous ruine, and deſolation of his fathers houſe. Was it not promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed as a bleſſing to <hi>Ioſiah</hi> that hee ſhould bee gathered to his fathers, and ſhuld not ſee the euill that came to paſſe immediatlie after his death? To the vngodly indeed it is a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment to bee taken from their
<pb facs="tcp:14455:19"/>heauen and pleaſure which they haue in this world, and to bee caſt into eternall torment after their life is ended:
<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 41.</note> and herehence it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, that death and <hi>the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance thereof</hi> is, and euer hath been, ſo <hi>bitter to them,</hi> becauſe they haue no hope, after this life is ended: according to that of <hi>Salomon,
<note place="margin">Prou. 11.7.</note> When a wicked man dieth all his hope is gone.</hi> Now what this benefit was that <hi>Henoch</hi> receiued, is very briefly noted in one worde <hi>veennenu,</hi> which the Vulgar tranſlateth,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>&amp; non appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruit,</hi> and hee appeared not. <hi>Tremel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius; &amp; non extitit,</hi> hee remained no more among men. <hi>Montanus,</hi> according to the Hebrew, <hi>&amp; non ille,</hi> hee was not: and the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to the Hebrewes hath <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, hee was tranſlated, that is, taken from the ſocietie of men, not by the vſuall way of death, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ende of all fleſh: but as hee in his bodie liued a heauenlie
<pb facs="tcp:14455:20"/>life, ſo was his bodie freed from or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary corruption, and receiued in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a heauenly condition, like thoſe that ſhall be found aliue at the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Chriſt, that in a moment ſhall be changed, and caught vp into the cloudes. And this tranſlation, and aſſumption of <hi>Henoch</hi> before the law;
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.1. Theſ. 4.</note> and <hi>Heliah</hi> vnder the law, did vndoubtedlie nouriſh the hope of the glorification of the bodies of the Saints, as types prefiguring the aſcenſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Chriſt, in whom the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of all heauenly glorie ſhould be performed and accompliſhed. Into what place he was receiued, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectures haue been diuers, al the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines of the Church of Rome, with ſome of the Ancients, affirme, that he with <hi>Eliah</hi> were placed in Paradiſe, that garden of Eden, whence <hi>Adam</hi> was expelled, and that they ſhall come at the latter end of the world to preach againſt Antichriſt; which is a meere conceit without any war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant
<pb facs="tcp:14455:20"/>or authoritie. Neither that place of the two witneſſes in the eleuenth of the Apocalyps, nor that of the 44. of Eccleſiaſticus, commonlie allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged for the proofe hereof, giue war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant to this imagination. Firſt,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Perceius</hi> is of this iudgement with manie others. Gen. 7.20.</note> for the place of Paradiſe, it was vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly drowned in the great deluge of the waters which were 15. cubites aboue the higheſt moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine. And by the geographical de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription thereof by <hi>Moſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 2.8.</note> it is appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent it was planted vpon the earth on the Eaſt part of <hi>Meſapotamia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Philo Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daeus.</hi>
               </note> neere Babylon, and not aboue the ſphere of the Moone,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>P. L. Sent. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>diſt.</hi> 17.</note> (as <hi>Peter Lom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bard,</hi> and others doe imagine.) The two witneſſes mentioned by S. <hi>Iohn</hi> (vſing a certaine number for an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine) ſignifie nothing elſe but that the Lord ſhould haue alwaies ſome, that in a holy zeale ſhould preach againſt the enemies of the truth, whom though the wicked ſhould kill and murther, yet ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:14455:21"/>they not ſo extinguiſhed gods ſpirit, but others ſhould ſtill bee raiſed vp (as hath bin in al ages of the church) to ſupplie their roomes in the Lords vineyard: the Lord neuer left him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe without witneſſes of his truth. And whereas they vrge a miracle in their raiſing to life againe, the like manner of ſpeaking is in the eight of Eccleſiaſtes,
<note place="margin">Eccle. 8.10.</note> 
               <hi>I haue ſeene the wicked bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried; and they returned;</hi> which no man euer vnderſtood of thoſe that were dead and buried, but of others as wicked as they which ſucceedinglie ſupplied their places.
<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 44.16.</note> The ſonne of <hi>Sirach</hi> calling <hi>Henoch</hi> an example of repentance to the generations, may with much more probabilitie be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of his tranſlation, then of any ſecond comming of him to bee expected, and of the generations that liued when he was ſo taken vp, that they ſhould bee mooued to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance by the knowledge of ſo great an honor done to ſo holy a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<pb facs="tcp:14455:21"/>(or made more inexcuſable) rather then of any other <hi>generations in the latter end of</hi> the world.</p>
            <p>Others doe hold, that <hi>Henoch</hi> was receiued vp into the higheſt hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens, <hi>in coelum beatorum:</hi> the place whither Chriſt did aſcend, and where the ſoules of the Saints reſt in happines, waiting for the reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But this opinion is contradicted by other Diuines very learned; as <hi>Peter Martir, Caluin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>P. M.</hi> vpon the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption of <hi>Heliah. Cal. Com. on this place.</hi>
               </note> and diuers more of the late writers: againſt which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion alſo is alleaged that place in the 10. Heb. verſ. 19.20. <hi>Wee may bee bold to enter into the holy place, by the new and liuing way which hee hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for vs through the vaile, that is,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Theophy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lact</hi> vpon this place.</note> his fleſh.</hi> That is, ſaith <hi>Theophylactus,</hi> this our Captaine firſt entred, hee went before and firſt made this paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage for vs; and therefore called a new way, becauſe Chriſt was the firſt that made it by his aſcenſion. To this end is alſo brought that place in the
<pb facs="tcp:14455:22"/>1. Cor. 15.23. <hi>Euery man in his owne order, the firſt fruits is Chriſt, afterward they that are of Chriſt,</hi> &amp;c. And alſo that place in Ioh. 3.13. where Chriſt ſaith: <hi>No man aſcendeth vp to heauen, but he that hath deſcended from heauen, that ſonne of man which is in heauen:</hi> (which I am not ignorant is other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe expounded, but it is not my purpoſe to ſtand vpon it.) Omitting therefore all coniecturall opinions, ſeeing the holy Scripture hath not made it manifeſt, modeſt ignorance is better then curious inquiſition.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Beza annot.</hi> Heb. 11.5.</note> For as a learned man ſaith, <hi>Temera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium eſt de his ſtatuere, curioſum inue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtigare:</hi> It is raſhnes to determine ſuch doubtfull things, and curioſitie to ſearch after them. <hi>The ſecret things belong to the Lord our God,
<note place="margin">Deut. 29.29.</note> but the things reueiled to vs, and to our chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren for euer, that wee may doe all the workes of this law. Melius est dubitare de occultis quàm litigare de in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certis:</hi> It is better to leaue hidden
<pb facs="tcp:14455:22"/>things in doubt, then to contend of things vncertaine. But howſoeuer, this is certaine, that <hi>Henoch</hi> was tranſlated into vnſpeakeable ioy and happines:
<note place="margin">Ioh. 14.2.</note> For the meaneſt of thoſe glorious manſions (whereof our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour ſaith in his fathers houſe there are manie) doe beyond all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon exceed the moſt glorious pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace or paradiſe vpon earth. The Lord ſo guide our hearts, and order our waies by his grace in our wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king on this vale of miſerie, that we may (like this holy man) keepe that ſtraite and narrow way that tendeth to eternal life, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> after our earthly pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimage is finiſhed, wee may bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued into that glorious reſt which is purchaſed for vs by the precious blood-ſhedding of our bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Ieſus Chriſt. To whom with the father and the holy Ghoſt be all honor and glorie now and for euer Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
